Leah: In the past children and young
people who showed signs of severe mental
illness such as Schizophrenia and bipolar
disorder, were thought to be not able to
function properly throughout life and may
never successfully contribute to society.
However, this is not the case when
handled appropriately with individuals
being involved in their own treatment.
Rhiannon: The recovery model is familiar
to most mental health practitioners and
psychologists, psychiatrists, doctors,
and other health professionals can
provide such support to some degree.
However, the connections and support
offered by family, friends, and other
peers can also be critical, along
with support groups and the community.
In particular, the recovery
model stresses the importance of
connectedness and social supports.
When children and young people have
supportive relationships that offer
unconditional love, they are better
able to cope with the symptoms of their
illness and work towards recovery.
Leah: The recovery model of mental
illness is often contrasted against
what is known as the medical model.
The medical model focuses on mental
disorders having physiological
causes, with treatment often
focused on the use of medications.
The two different models are often
presented as being in opposition
to one another, but they can be
complementary and can be used together.
Rhiannon: While the medical model
ensures that physiological causes are
fully addressed, the recovery model
ensures that individuals are able to be
directly involved in their own treatment,
offering them personal empowerment,
and the family or peer support needed
to cope with their illness and help
them work towards getting better.
Leah: One of the recovery model’s
major benefits is that it focuses
on the individual’s strengths and
abilities in knowing their own
experiences and to be able to take
an active role in their treatment.